<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd at the funeral of The Right Honourable the Lady Guilford, Nov. 18, 1699 by John Knight ...</title>
            <author>Knight, John, 1651-1712.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47541</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K689</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1128</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13429138</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13429138</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99507</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47541)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99507)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 461:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd at the funeral of The Right Honourable the Lady Guilford, Nov. 18, 1699 by John Knight ...</title>
                  <author>Knight, John, 1651-1712.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for George Thorp ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Guilford, Elizabeth Greville North, --  Baroness, 1669-1699.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99507:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd at the FUNERAL OF The Right Honourable THE Lady <hi>GUILFORD,</hi> Nov. 18. 1699.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Knight,</hi> D. D. Rector of <hi>Broughton,</hi> in <hi>Oxfordſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>George Thorp,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Banbury,</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:99507:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99507:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE THE Lord <hi>GUILFORD.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE following Diſcourſe is herewith humbly offered to your Lordſhip, in Obedience to Your Commands. And tho' I cannot doubt of its Acceptance there, where I have receiv'd ſo many Pledges of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect; yet had I been left free, this ſhould have been the laſt Thing I would have choſen, by which to expreſs my Thankfulneſs, and my Duty.</p>
            <p>The ſad Solemnity being perform'd late in the Evening, I was obliged to drop ſeveral Paragraphs, that I had prepar'd to ſpeak, which are here ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in their proper Place.</p>
            <p>As for the Defects which ſtill remain, I can only ask Your Pardon, SIR, but cannot remedy 'em.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:99507:3"/>I had neither Skill nor Colours, to draw ſo bright and Heavenly a Life; the Piety and Devotion She daily practis'd, gave Her ſuch Perfections as were eaſily Admir'd, but ſcarce poſſible to be deſcrib'd.</p>
            <p>And now, my Lord, if inſtead of votive Tables to adorn Her Shrine, Your Lordſhip ſhall preſerve Her Memory, by imitating Her Example, You alſo ſhall be kept by the Power of God, through Faith, unto Salvation; which is the Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhip's, in the Humbleſt and moſt Dutiful Obſervance,</hi> John Knight.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99507:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>NUMB. XXIII. Latter part of the 10th Verſe.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>Let me dye the Death of the Righteous, and let my laſt end be like his.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WHICH Words are the Sober and Pious Wiſh of a very impious, and otherwiſe very profane Man; who, tho' out of a greedy Appetite after Gain, had ſold himſelf to work a moſt deſperate piece of Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, even to compaſs an Inchantment againſt <hi>Jacob,</hi> and thereby ruin <hi>Iſrael,</hi> God's only Heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, by Magick and Sorcery; yet the Spirit of God ſo effectually over-ruled the Rage of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and the Malice of his Familiar, that he could not curſe nor defie, but altogether bleſs'd them.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>Moab,</hi> whoſe Drudgery <hi>Balaam</hi> was to do, built his Altars to <hi>Baal,</hi> the reigning Idol of that Age and Nation; at his Oracles the Prophet was to conſult, and from them receive his Commiſſion, to go and curſe <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And after he had thus affronted God by ſacrificing to the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99507:4"/>
Devil, he was, one would think, hopefully diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, both to curſe and to bewitch his People.</p>
            <p>But obſerve the turn God gave to his wicked Enterprize, which will afford us equal matter of Comfort and Amazement; the Devil had the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, but God gave the Anſwer, and the Oracle ſtood dumb, whilſt the Angel of the Lord pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd the devoted People Bleſſed.</p>
            <p>Wherefore ſurely there can be no miſchievous Divination againſt <hi>Jacob,</hi> when <hi>Jacob</hi>'s God reſolves to bleſs the Augury, and make the Magician his own Prophet. And what could <hi>Balak</hi> or Satan do to vex <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when their God proclaim'd Peace to them, from the very Altars of <hi>Baal;</hi> turning the Magick Circle into Holy Ground, and forcing that Tongue, of which the Devil had poſſeſſion, to declare his Goodneſs and Loving-kindneſs to his People? For after many fruitleſs, tho' very deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Attempts to curſe that People, <hi>Balaam</hi> perceiv'd the Bleſſing was fatal, and the Decree of it irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſible, <hi>v.</hi> 20. inſomuch that he ſaw cauſe to wiſh himſelf imbark'd in their Bottom, that their final Lot might be his own; <hi>Let me dye the Death of the Righteous,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>From which Words, and the Occaſion of them, were it ſuitable to that <hi>Occaſion</hi> on which we are now aſſembled, I could advance, and proſecute
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99507:4"/>
ſeveral very grave, and important Obſervations; As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Obſ.</hi> That to be eſtabliſh'd in the Divine Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, as the Lord's Peculiar, is certainly the ſafeſt, and moſt honourable Condition of Being, even in this Life. For in this inſtance, under our preſent Conſideration, you ſee neither Men nor Devils can annoy thoſe whom God undertakes to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and uphold.</p>
            <p>'Tis all impotent Malice that ſets upon any Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to them. However they are threatned, or how deſperately ſoever they are expoſed, how bold ſoever their Enemies may be; tho' they ſhew it firſt in defying God, which beſpeaks the utmoſt, even an helliſh Rage; yet ſo obſtinate is the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and ſo ſecure the Shelter which God's Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have under his Protection, that the very Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of Satan, employ'd to buffet them, ſhall find their Powers controul'd, their Artillery turn'd upon themſelves, and the Holy Spirit will caſt out Satan; the mad Diviner ſhall revolt, and become the Lord's Prophet, to pronounce that People bleſſed, whom he took Fees to curſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Obſ.</hi> The prevailing Force and Evidence of Divine Truths, which prophane or Atheiſtical Wits, either queſtion or deny: Thoſe Articles, upon the belief of which God has eſtabliſht his own Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99507:5"/>
and thence challenges our Reverence and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration, however they are exploded by the Luſts of Infidels, the Wit of Atheiſts, or the Malice of Devils, will one time or other be effectually preſt home, to the Conviction of thoſe that ſcoff at them.</p>
            <p>For ſee here, how unlikely a Man was <hi>Balaam</hi> to ſay any thing in Honour of the true God, or to aſſert the peculiar Prerogative of his Providence in the Government of the World; who was himſelf fallen into the groſſeſt Idolatry, giving Divine Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours to the Devil, and in his Name, and by his Power attempting to bring the utmoſt Reproach upon the Name, and upon the Church of God. And yet you ſee the prophane Wretch could not peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably dye in his Impiety; tho' 'tis to be fear'd he did dye in it; but renouncing his Magick, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes himſelf to his Prayers, and deſpiſing his own Idol; when he conſulted his own Happineſs on that Occaſion, he gave Glory to God, tho' he had ſo lately ſold, and devoted himſelf to celebrate and eſtabliſh the Worſhip of a damn'd Idol.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Obſ.</hi> The commanding Influence, and awful Majeſty there is in a virtuous and holy Life. Its avowed Enemies, in their ſober moods, and if ever they reflect, do conſtantly commend its ſide. The King of <hi>Moab</hi>'s Treaſury, with all the Riches in it, <hi>Balaam</hi> thought too mean to purchaſe the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99507:5"/>
or the Happineſs that attends a Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and a good Man; nor now eſpecially, when he took the proſpect of Death and Judgment, could it calm the Tempeſt of his amaz'd Conſcience.</p>
            <p>To die the death of Kings, or Stateſmen, was too ſtupid a wiſh even for ſuch a Man as <hi>Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am.</hi> And this, without that other Cognizance and Qualification, which Piety and Holineſs, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion to the true God gives a Man, is to dye wretched and contemptible, full of Horrours or void of ſenſe: That is, a man muſt at the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of his laſt End, look either like a Beaſt or a Devil, tho' he were a great Prince, and had acquir'd the Reputation of being never ſo wiſe or powerful, rich or learned.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Obſ.</hi> From this early Inſtance of Heatheniſh Idolatry and Profaneneſs, we may obſerve, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail the deſperate Degeneracy of the Age we live in; in that the very ſame Abomination ſhould be ſet up and practis'd ſo commonly as they ſay it is among the inferiour ſort of People, eſpecially in ſuch a Church, and ſuch a Nation as this! That after Men have given up their Names to Chriſt, been initiated his Diſciples by a ſolemn inſtituted Rite of his moſt Holy Religion; after they have made an open Renunciation of God's Enemies, and their own, and devoted themſelves the entire
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99507:6"/>
Servants of God and Chriſt, and engaged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a Covenant to live and dye ſo; a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant that eſtabliſhes their Title to ſuch bleſſed Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, as the very Angels admire, and which were purchaſed for us at no leſs a Price than the Life of God! In a word, that after all the clear and gracious Declarations of God's Mind and Will in this Particular, ſo many poor Souls, whom Chriſt died to ſave, ſhould revolt from the Captain of their Salvation, refuſe their own Mercies, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do themſelves for ever, by running greedily after the Error of this very <hi>Balaam, for Reward,</hi> as St. <hi>Jude</hi> expreſſes it; this, I ſay, to any ſerious Man, muſt occaſion but a Melancholick Entertainment. The People I mean, are thoſe poor deluded Wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, who fly to Wizards and Diviners, ſuch as they call Cunning Men, for the redreſs of any providential Evil or Diſaſter, under which they ſuffer.</p>
            <p>Now foreſeeing that People of this Size would throng in, to make up the biggeſt part of this great Aſſembly, I was loath, upon ſo proper an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as I have in hand, and on ſo grave an Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion as this, to ſlip the Advantage of dropping ſo ſerious and ſeaſonable an Admonition.</p>
            <p>Theſe poor Creatures it ſeems, in any manner of Diſtreſs, very ordinarily, with <hi>Saul</hi> apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99507:6"/>
to Witches and Inchantments for Relief. And can there be a ſadder Story told than this, that profeſt Chriſtians ſhould be given up to ſuch a reprobate Senſe, as to take the Devil for Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar, and by the moſt damnable Apoſtacy, pay their Devotion there, where they have been taught to expect their everlaſting Torments!</p>
            <p>For to apply our ſelves to the uſe of ſuch means as Charms and Inchantments, upon any occaſion whatſoever, is an Atheiſtical Diſclaimer of our Dependance upon God's Providence, and the moſt provoking Affront that can be offer'd to his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>Will it be ſaid, (as I have heard it ſaid in their Excuſe,) that they uſe theſe means with an harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs intent, yea with a religious Truſt in God, that he will bleſs them, to their Relief?</p>
            <p>But this is worſe than to lye for God; this is to pretend to own him, in an Inſtance wherein they do in Fact renounce him. This may be call'd the Religion of Atheiſm, for 'tis affronting God with Solemnity, and denying him with Devotion. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides it is ſo ridiculous a Conceit, that the erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an odd Figure, and a parcel of ſenſeleſs Gibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, ſhould raiſe a ſinking Pulſe, repair the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cays of Nature, or bring back loſt Goods, except it be by the Power of the Devil; That God has in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99507:7"/>
Mercy left us, in this <hi>Balaam</hi>'s Story, a demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Argument, not only of the impious Profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it, but of its ſtupid Folly, by opening the Mouth of a contemptible Aſs, to rebuke the Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the great Magician.</p>
            <p>And now let us behold him, as he ſtands thus ſuitably corrected, and we ſhall ſee this very Man in a much better mood; and yielding himſelf up to be acted by a more powerful and purer Spirit, he becomes a Preacher of that very Faith, which he had ſo lately perſecuted, even a Preacher of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs and the Reſurrection. I dare not be po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive, that <hi>Balaam,</hi> tho' ſo eminent a Prophet, had an expreſs Revelation made to him of this Doctrine; for 'tis probable, if not certain, that many of the Prophets were made uſe of to predict ſuch future E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents, as they themſelves did not perfectly and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apprehend. Tho', if it be as juſt an Obſervation as it ſeems to be a judicious one, which Monſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eur <hi>Alix</hi> has made (in his Reflections on the four laſt Books of <hi>Moſes,</hi> Cap. XI.) on <hi>Balaam</hi>'s Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, <hi>viz.</hi> That in it he makes a very diſtinct mention of the future Calling of the Gentiles to the Faith, <hi>Numb.</hi> 24.17. (Now I ſay, if ſo) it may be as eaſie to allow him to have a Foreſight and Belief of the Reſurrection; this being the great Article of that Faith to which the Gentiles
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99507:7"/>
were call'd by the Servants of the Meſſiah, in their Preaching of the Goſpel. But let that be as it will, 'tis certain <hi>Balaam</hi> had the knowledge and belief of a ſtate of Immortality, and of future Rewards and Puniſhments; and ſo much has been generally acknowledg'd by the Learned Fathers and Doctors of the Chriſtian Church, to be his Intention and meaning in theſe Words of my Text; it being the Foreſight of this, that urged him to ſuch a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in crying out, <hi>Let me dye,</hi> &amp;c. But far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, this is certain, if we may believe <hi>Diogenes Laertius, (Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Vit. Philoſ.)</hi> there were ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the Eaſtern <hi>Magi,</hi> among whom <hi>Balaam</hi> is generally reckon'd one, that taught this expreſs Doctrine, that Men after Death ſhould return back to Life, and be Immortal; and this he publiſhes to the World, upon the Authority of <hi>Theopompus,</hi> who was one of them, and who ſays in the Eighth of his <hi>Philippics,</hi> this Doctrine is <hi>juxta Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorum Sententiam;</hi> the ſame is ſupported by the Authorities of <hi>Rhodius</hi> and <hi>Eudemus.</hi> But tho' theſe Teſtimonies were rejected, yet in the ſubſequent Context, this Prophet, is by almoſt all that believe the Divine Revelations, underſtood to propheſie very clearly of Chriſt, and the Kingdom of the Meſſiah. He ſays of Chriſt that <hi>he ſhall have the Dominion, Chap.</hi> 24. <hi>v.</hi> 19. But we know that his
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99507:8"/>
Reſurrection was the firſt glorious Manifeſtation of his Royal Power, in his Conqueſt over Death and Hell. And in this ſtate why might not <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam</hi> behold him, eſpecially after he knew the Knowledge of the moſt High, and had ſeen the Viſion of the Almighty, upon which he declar'd, <hi>I ſhall ſee him, but not now,</hi> v. 17. But to diſpute for the Prophet's meaning no longer, be it what it will, ſure I am, that the laſt end of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous cannot be by us underſtood, to mean any thing ſhort of the Reſurrection: For <hi>the Death of the righteous and the wicked,</hi> by the beſt Judgment we can make, is often ſo little preferrable one to th' other, that there can be no ſenſe in our wiſhing rather for that than this, unleſs upon the ſteady Conviction and Belief of their riſing again to an Immortal Life.</p>
            <p>And now I am come to treat of the Text, as in a true, ſo in a ſenſe very ſuitable to the ſad Occaſion, on which we are now met.</p>
            <p>For what ſo proper to allay our Sorrows for the Death of our Friends, or to prompt us to all ſerious Preparations to follow them, as to be told, at their Interment, that the Body we commit to the Duſt ſhall again be quicken'd, tho' it periſh there; and tho' <hi>ſown in Diſhonour,</hi> yet not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hopes it ſhall be <hi>rais'd in Glory.</hi> Wherefore
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99507:8"/>
in purſuit of the utmoſt intention of the Words, the <hi>Altior Senſus, &amp; Myſticus,</hi> as <hi>Grotius</hi> ſpeaks, I ſhall hold my ſelf accountable for this twofold Undertaking.</p>
            <p n="1">I. I ſhall ſhew the Doctrine of the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on has not been only anciently and generally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd, but the Reaſon of it, which makes it neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary; and therefore not without abſurdity to be denyed.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The Article being prov'd, I ſhall ſhew for what ſingular Reaſons the laſt end of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous is incomparably moſt deſirable; ſo that it will be our Wiſdom not only to wiſh it may be our own, but alſo ſeriouſly to endeavour it.</p>
            <p n="1">I. As for the Doctrine of the Reſurrection, we may the leſs wonder it has been ſo generally receiv'd, it being an Article of ſo vaſt moment to be believ'd, that <hi>Theophylact</hi> fears not to call it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Capital Article of our Faith. And a greater than he ſays, If it be not true, <hi>our Faith, i. e.</hi> our Religion, is good for nothing; 'tis a Scheme of Vanity, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. Nay St. <hi>Paul</hi> eſteemed it ſo conſiderable, that, as if the whole of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion was contain'd in it, he calls it (<hi>v.</hi> 1. of that Chap.) <hi>the Goſpel.</hi> Yea, we will abſolve the whole Rabble of Deiſts, Atheiſts, Sceptics, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, from all their Blaſphemy and Scurrility,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99507:9"/>
and ſay with them, our Religion is an Impoſture, and its holy Author a Cheat, if with any tolerable Senſe, or ſhew of Reaſon, the Truth of it can be queſtion'd.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, to be as clear and quick as may be, in the diſpatch of this Head, I will</p>
            <p n="1">1. Evince the Truth of our Saviour's Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Then ſhew the neceſſary Connexion there is betwixt his and ours, <hi>i. e.</hi> Becauſe he is riſen, we ſhall alſo infallibly be rais'd from the dead.</p>
            <p n="1">1. My buſineſs is to prove that Chriſt is riſen. And if there had not been one Witneſs of it in the World, the Prophecies that foretold it would have been infinite Satisfaction to every Man, that had but <hi>Balaam</hi>'s modeſty to believe, that <hi>God is not a Man that he ſhould lie,</hi> v. 19.</p>
            <p>The Spirit of Prophecy is that undeniable Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony to <hi>Jeſus</hi> and his Reſurrection, that to all Men that can believe the Truth or the Power of God, it is and has been always eſteem'd beyond any ſort of Proof or Evidence whatſoever.</p>
            <p>So ſtrong an Argument of the Event are all the Predictions of the Holy Ghoſt, that things are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid in Scripture to be done, becauſe they are foretold. Were there then any Prophecies to this purpoſe, which Holy Men of old ſpoke, as they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99507:9"/>
were moved by the Holy Ghoſt? This is ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that our Saviour ventur'd the whole Credit of the Fact, rather upon this, than upon any other Teſtimonies; inſomuch that he told the <hi>Jews,</hi> if they did not believe <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Writings, <hi>neither would they believe, tho' one roſe from the dead.</hi> And this method of Proof he took to perſwade his own Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples: Tho' theſe Men had ſeen him often, and had converſt with him, tho' they had eat and drank, walkt and diſcourſt with him, and were hereby in no manner of doubt concerning the Truth of his being riſen, (except <hi>Thomas,</hi> for whoſe ſatisfaction he expoſed his Wounds to be ſearcht and hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by him) yet notwithſtanding all this, he ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges what had been prophecy'd of his Reſurrection, to give them the <hi>greateſt</hi> Aſſurance of it, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms their Faith by a ſurer Evidence, for <hi>then open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he their Underſtandings, that they might underſtand the Scriptures, ſaying, thus it is written, and thus it behoved Chriſt to ſuffer, and to riſe from the Dead.</hi> Luke 24.45, 46.</p>
            <p>The ſame Argument St. <hi>Peter,</hi> though he was himſelf an Eye-witneſs, urged as the chiefeſt Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the reality of the Miracle, and as the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſupport of their Faith in it, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17, <hi>&amp; ſeq.</hi> They were theſe Predictions that made him as well the Expectation as the Deſire of all Ages.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:99507:10"/>Yea, it was after all ſo plainly foretold by our Saviour himſelf, and the Impreſſion of his Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction wrought with ſuch Force upon the Minds of his Enemies, that his very Murderers did expect it; it being from hence they were prompted to guard his Tomb; which by the unſearchable Wiſdom of God was the occaſion to theſe Wretches, of ſuch further Evidence, that they were at Charges to ſtifle what they therefore wanted the Impudence to deny: For next to the Angels, the Guards that were hired to keep him Priſoner in the Grave, were ſome of the firſt Evangeliſts to publiſh the Truth of his Reſurrection, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.11. So that upon their Report, the Chief Prieſts and Elders were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd in their Belief on't.</p>
            <p>And how impoſſible muſt it have been for thoſe Infidels to hold out in the real Disbelief of it, when they had obſerv'd the ancient Prophecies were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in him, with reſpect to ſome of the minuteſt Circumſtances and Tranſactions of his Life; yea when they had ſeen ſeveral Perſons, whom they had known truly dead, were reſtored to Life by him; and one particularly, <hi>Lazarus</hi> by Name, not only dead but rotten.</p>
            <p>Now was it likely, or could they imagine, that he that had given ſuch Evidence of his Almighty Power, and ſo openly diſplay'd his Conqueſts o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99507:10"/>
the Grave, was liable himſelf to be held Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive by the Enemy he had vanquiſh'd?</p>
            <p>Upon the whole then, if Chriſt, as you have heard, laid the greateſt weight upon, and chiefly appeal'd unto the ancient Prophecies that foretold his Reſurrection, our modern Atheiſts and Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels have nothing to do, but to examin whether there are any Prophecies extant of ſuch a Date. And if they find any ſuch, they muſt in ſpight of their Teeth confeſs, that the Accompliſhment of them is an immoveable Teſtimony to the Foreknowledge and Wiſdom, to the infinite Power and Truth of God.</p>
            <p>Again, that what was thus prophecy'd of Chriſt, and particularly of his Reſurrection, has according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly been fulfill'd. This God himſelf has born ſuch undeniable Witneſs unto, <hi>both with Signs and Wonders, and divers Miracles, and gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his own Will,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.4. that the Infidel has not the leaſt colour of Pretence to diſpute its Evidence. Inſomuch that his Wit and Malice is quite exhauſted upon the Argument. And except we will admit of Scoffs for Objections, and Grimaces for Confutations, the poor Atheiſt and his Cauſe are ruin'd; for whatever Reaſons he brings to weaken or ſubvert the Credit of this Doctrine, or of them that have teſtify'd to the Truth of it, will equally affect his own Credit, tho' what he
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99507:11"/>
affirms be really never ſo true, and tho' it were infinitely his Intereſt that it obtain'd Belief.</p>
            <p>Wherefore all that I ſhall here further add upon this Argument is, That upon the Credit of thoſe Prophecies that foretold the Reſurrection, and thoſe Eye-witneſſes that ſaw Chriſt riſen, it was generally believed by almoſt all Nations, and all ſorts of men; by the Patriarchs and <hi>Magi,</hi> by <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> by Philoſophers of all Sects, yea by <hi>Judas</hi> that betrayed him, by the Judges that condemned him, and by the Executioner that diſpatch'd him; for when he, <hi>the Centurion,</hi> i. e. the Heathen Officer who had the care of his Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, <hi>ſaw what was done, he fear'd greatly,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Truly this was the Son of God.</hi> Matt. 27.54. For he that was ſeen and felt to exerciſe ſuch a power, that put the Earth into Convulſions whilſt he was dying upon the Croſs, left no room in any Infidel to doubt after that, but he could al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo rend the Priſon of the Grave, as he did by a ſecond Earth-quake at his powerful Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>Thus did he, that ſuffer'd for our Sins, to ſhew the efficacy of that Attonement, riſe again for the Juſtification both of it and us; which makes our aſſurance of our Reſurrection equal to that of his; and that if we believe he is riſen, with the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99507:11"/>
ſame certainty are we to believe that we ſhall: For <hi>if there be no Reſurrection of the Dead, then neither is Chriſt riſen,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> argues 1 Cor. 15. Which brings me to my ſecond Particular to be prov'd, <hi>viz.</hi> The neceſſary Connexion between his and ours.</p>
            <p>Chriſt is the head of that Body, of which we are ſaid to be members, and by his Reſurrection he hath begotten us to a lively hope of our own; for <hi>if the Spirit of him who raiſed up Jeſus from the Dead, dwell in you; he that raiſed up Chriſt from the Dead, ſhall alſo quicken your mortal Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, by his Spirit that dwelleth in you.</hi> Rom. 8.11. So that if Death had no more power over him, who took upon him to expiate for our Sins, which brought the puniſhment of Death upon us, (for Death was the conſequent of our ſinning, not the fate of our Nature) it muſt needs follow, that it can have no more power over us; otherwiſe our Puniſhment would remain after our Guilt is taken off, which cannot be ſaid, without robbing God of the Attribute of his Juſtice, as well as Chriſt of the Merits of his Croſs. Wherefore <hi>as by the firſt</hi> Adam <hi>came Death, by the ſecond came alſo the Reſurrection of the Dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſhort, as I have above prov'd, that the moſt undoubted Argument of Chriſt's Reſurrection,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99507:12"/>
were the Prophecies that foretold it; ſo have we the like aſſurance from the Declarations of God's Will concerning ours too: And if there be no doubt of God's Power, but that he is <hi>able,</hi> there can be none of his purpoſe in this matter, ſince he has aſſur'd us, that he <hi>will;</hi> and therefore we have now nothing to do, but to believe it <hi>neceſſary.</hi> Wherefore <hi>marvel not at this, for the hour com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, in which all that are in the Grave ſhall hear his voice, and come forth; they that have done good unto the Reſurrection of Life, and they that have done evil unto the Reſurrection of Damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> John 5.28, 29. We may have leave, and 'tis indeed our duty, to admire and adore the grace and efficacy of ſuch an Operation, but 'tis unpardonable to wonder ſo, as to ſuſpect the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty. We may devoutly admire, that Bodies ſo frail as ours ſhould become ſubjects of Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality: And to hear how the Almighty Potter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns to form ſuch lumps of Clay into everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Veſſels of honour, is, one would think, enough to perſwade us in the mean time, to reverence our Bodies more, than to defile them by ſenſuality, to oppreſs them by Intemperance, and ruine them for a Luſt. <hi>Once more,</hi> It juſtly may and ought to raiſe our wonder and devotion both, to be told, That 'tis by his Power and Goodneſs we ſhall be
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99507:12"/>
reſcued from the Grave, who was himſelf by our inhumane Malice ſent thither. Is he to come and fetch us from the Grave, who comes with Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments dyed in his own Blood, and ſo brings with him the Remembrances of our Cruelty? It is ſo; and therefore, as I ſaid, tho' we are forbid to marvel ſo as to diſtruſt the faithfulneſs of his Promiſe, or the omnipotence of his Power, yet not to be affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with all aſtoniſhment and devotion at the conſideration of it, might be eſteemed another Miracle.</p>
            <p>And thus have I endeavoured, with competent ſatisfaction I hope, the diſcharge of my firſt task, <hi>viz.</hi> the proof of this great Article of our Faith; tho' conſidering there are ſtill ſome Atheiſtical Gainſayers, that except againſt the Article and the Proof of it, I muſt be obliged to pay ſome deference to them, eſpecially ſince they diſtinguiſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by their Numbers, and by their Wit, by their polite Manners, and politer Learning: Nay they ſay theſe Heathens boaſt the Reverſe of <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi>'s Apology for the Chriſtians, and tell us, that they fill our Courts, our Camps, and our chiefeſt Cities; But what occaſion ſoever there is for ſo impudent a Vapour, let thoſe that are moſt concerned in the reproach on't look to't; mean while I return to what theſe Gentlemen ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept againſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:99507:13"/>And, 1. They tell us, that this Doctrine was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver generally receiv'd, but men of the acuteſt wit and deepeſt judgment always oppoſed it, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as early as it was publickly attempted to be impoſed upon their credulity. Among the <hi>Greeks,</hi> the <hi>Epicureans</hi> and <hi>Stoicks</hi> derided it, and among the <hi>Jews</hi> the <hi>Saducees</hi> obſtinately denyed it, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. and <hi>Acts</hi> 17.18.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> True this is, and let our Infidels make the moſt on't: And after all it will appear, that they were but <hi>ſome</hi> among the <hi>Corinthians, i. e.</hi> ſome odd inconſiderable Folk; a deſpicable Sect among the <hi>Jews,</hi> but of late date, and ſhort continuance, whom the Learned Hiſtorian, of their own Age and Nation, deſcribes as very contemptible for their Numbers and their Manners. So alſo in the other Inſtance, they were not all the Schools of <hi>Athens,</hi> but <hi>certain</hi> of the <hi>Epicureans</hi> and <hi>Stoicks;</hi> as if not all theſe neither. But whoever reads <hi>Epicurus</hi> their Maſter's Epiſtle to <hi>Herodotus, [apud Diog. Laert.]</hi> will not wonder his Scholars and Succeſſors ſhould affirm any thing abſurdly, or deny what may be evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prov'd true; ſince he there aſſerts the Infinity of Bodies, and calls it Dotage to aſſert the Soul in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporeal; which <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> a greater than he, and his Predeceſſor in the ſame School, very rationally affirm'd. So that theſe Exceptions rather confirm
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99507:13"/>
the Doctrine, than make any valuable Objection a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</p>
            <p>And indeed of extraordinary uſe they prov'd in his Almighty Hand, who can bring Light out of Darkneſs; for it was thro' the ſenſeleſs Incredulity and Pertneſs of theſe few Men, that the Arguments were multiply'd in defence of the Doctrine, 'till it became eſtabliſht ſo, as to be impoſſible to ſhake it.</p>
            <p>For tho' the <hi>Corinthians</hi> Infidelity was occaſion'd by a fooliſh Enquiry into the manner how the dead were rais'd? And with what Body do they come? Yet the acute Argument the Apoſtle brought to ſatisfie thoſe Fools, and to ſolve the myſterious <hi>Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomenon</hi> ſo far, as to take off all pretence of Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity, in affirming it of the ſame Body, is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely more rational than their ſtrongeſt Exceptions. For he illuſtrates it by Grain, which he ſays is not quicken'd except it dye; and by dying it is quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en'd, even the very <hi>ſame</hi> Grain. For 'tis generally now acknowledg'd, that the Seeds of Plants do contain every individual part of the entire Bodies, <hi>in parvo,</hi> which ſpring from them, and that the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of more Seed, is nothing elſe but the Nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Augmentation of the parts of the very ſame Seed.</p>
            <p>And for this reaſon, the Apoſtle ſpeaking of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99507:14"/>
Seed-corn, uſes ſuch Words as are proper to our Bodies, that they dye, and are quicken'd; and of our Bodies he ſpeaks in a Stile more proper unto Seeds, that they are <hi>ſown;</hi> to ſhew, ſays <hi>Theophil.</hi> the parallel Identity in the Reſurrection of Both. And after this curious Solution of the difficulty, as a Philoſophical Enquiry, he would not indulge theſe Men in the leaſt Thought, as if there were not ineffable Myſtery in the Reſurrection, for he tells them 'tis a Myſtery, but he has ſhew'd it not unreaſonable; but a Myſtery it muſt remain after all that can be ſaid, ſince <hi>this corruptible puts on In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruption, and this mortal Immortality.</hi> And this St. <hi>Paul,</hi> after he had been rapt up into Heaven, could neither expreſs nor explain, but tells us, <hi>it cannot be underſtood, nor can it enter into the Heart of Man to conceive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I haſten now to take notice of one Objection, which the Adverſary brings, directly to confront my chiefeſt Argument, by which I would eſtabliſh the Article of the Reſurrection, which was by the Authority of the ſacred Canon, and the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of inſpir'd Pen-men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> And 'tis objected, upon the Authority of the wiſeſt of Men, that <hi>that which befalleth the Sons of Men, befalleth Beaſts; as the one dyes, ſo dyes the other; yea, they have all one Breath, ſo that a Man hath no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminence
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99507:14"/>
above a Beaſt,</hi> Eccleſ. 3.19. And upon the Authority of <hi>David,</hi> a Man as eminent for Piety, as <hi>Solomon</hi> his Son for Wiſdom, we are aſſur'd the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle is plainly given up, for he in his very Devotions to his God (and ſure he was in earneſt then) ſays, that after Death he was to <hi>be no more,</hi> Pſ. 39.13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Now whatever real weight there is in this Objection, 'tis certain, they that offer it lay none upon it, but deſpiſe it. For the Deiſts, whoſe it is, (we muſt no more call them Atheiſts, becauſe they profeſs to believe a God) tho' they own the Being of a God, yet deſire to be excus'd the believing any thing he ſays. And therefore you muſt know, when they read the Scriptures, 'tis only to learn how to make Speeches in their Diſgrace, and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme God in the Words of his own Mouth. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſomewhat muſt be ſaid to it, and ſince the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling any one of theſe Texts, will take off the force of both, I ſhall therefore attempt it upon the laſt, as that which in its ſound, and form of the Expreſſion, does more literally and directly import a denyal of Man's Immortality, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of his Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>But the moſt ignorant will eaſily perceive this could not be <hi>David</hi>'s Meaning, that after Death he was to <hi>be no more,</hi> when they are ſhew'd the ſcope of his Prayer; for tho' he was an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99507:15"/>
Man, and had labour'd hard to recover the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of God, which by his former Sins he had ſo deſperately hazarded, yet he knew it was ſo infinite an Intereſt he had to ſecure, that he could never do too much for't; and now being apprehenſive his Life was in danger by the Violence of his proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous Enemies, as well as by the frailty of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, he earneſtly pray'd that God would pleaſe ſome way or other to diſcover to him the Period of his Days, that he might make ſuitable Preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for ſuch a change; and ſince after this Life is finiſht, all our holy Travels are ſo too, and nothing can be done for Heaven on the other ſide the Grave; he begs for a little more time and ſtrengh, that he might do God more, and more acceptable Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, before he <hi>went hence,</hi> and ſhould do no more. And this was evidently the direct Meaning and Scope of his Supplication. For that this wiſe and great King ſhould deſire further to ſpin out this weary Life, which he had ſo long experimented to be ſo full of Sorrows, and more, that he ſhould pray for more time to ſpend in Holy Mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the Labours of Religion; in recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending himſelf to the Divine Favour, by more ſignal Acts of Faith and Patience, of Obedience and Submiſſion, and yet expect that after Death he was to <hi>be no more;</hi> this is ſo unlikely, that 'tis hard to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99507:15"/>
charge him with any thing more abſurd. For the Labours of Religion are many of them ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the eaſe and happineſs of <hi>this</hi> Life, that 'tis impoſſible to attempt them, but upon the ſtrongeſt aſſurances and expectations of <hi>another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed, if <hi>David</hi> had only aimed at the enlarg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Conqueſts, or deſign'd to paſs his days in eaſe and ſloth, had he intended to make his Life a Scene of coſtly Pleaſures, and to have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed himſelf by an indulgence to mighty Luſts, ſacrificing the Blood and Purſes of his ſubjects to his exceſſive Riots, there had been ſome ſenſe in deſiring a long Life, and a brisker health, upon the ſuppoſition, that after Death he was to be no more; but ſince he prayed for more Strength, only to Miniſter to his more vigorous Devotions, and to enable him to ſuſtain the pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Travels of Repentance, and a ſevere Virtue; 'tis certain he proceeded herein upon the full per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion and hopes of a better Life. But enough of this; for the literal meaning of the words without doubt is embraced at any time by theſe men, as agreeable rather to their luſtful wiſhes, than to the ſober Sentiments of their minds. I ſay the <hi>ſober Sentiments</hi> of their Minds: For even theſe men I muſt believe are ſeldom ſo far har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den'd and debauch'd, but that they have their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervals
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99507:16"/>
of Recollection, and in this ſeaſon to my knowledge, whatever is the occaſion, they will frankly profeſs, they would willingly exchange their hopes for their fears, and they would give up their expectancies of any <hi>Inheritance</hi> among the <hi>Saints,</hi> if they could but be aſſured, they ſhould have their <hi>Portion</hi> among <hi>Dogs.</hi> i. e. They would not care for the <hi>Felicities,</hi> provided they could e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape the Immortal <hi>Miſeries</hi> of the other Life.</p>
            <p>Now theſe miſgiving thoughts are ſtrong pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages even to themſelves, that after Death they ſhall not ceaſe to be. But this vile Epicure that cries, <hi>let us eat and drink, for to morrow we die,</hi> is embolden'd to make ſuch a profeſſion over his Wine only, and whilſt he is enſlav'd to the Pleaſures of the Palate; tho' when that Beaſt is diſciplin'd into a diſtaſte of his luſcious Entertainments, and is made by adverſity to <hi>conſider,</hi> that his Life is more than Food, and his Belly infinitely leſs and inferiour to his God, he will ſcarce fail then, if not to believe, yet to fear and tremble at the apprehenſions of another Life. 'Tis a prodigious Atheiſt, that can hold out for ever remorſeleſs and unſhaken: Tho' they ſay theſe men have their Dypticks too, in which there are enroll'd all the famous inſtances of unrelenting Atheiſts, which are carefully Preſerv'd to encourage the weak, and to inſpirit thoſe that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99507:16"/>
are in Danger, by the infinite arts and methods of the Holy Ghoſt's operating upon their Souls, to revolt back to God: And conſidering the Power of God's wrath, we can't well queſtion, but theſe Sinners againſt their Souls, may be delivered up to ſo Reprobate a ſenſe. But however, if theſe wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es have ever any Workings of mind, any Snubs of Conſcience, any Spiritual Terrours, any waking Frights, or Ghaſtly Dreams like other men, theſe having often no manner of Relation to, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance upon the Body, are inſuperable convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, that the Soul is an Immaterial Being, and that as it can act thus independantly upon the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ſo 'tis the extreameſt abſurdity to believe it ſhall die with it.</p>
            <p>But whatever ſuch Scoffers may believe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Soul's Immortality, or the Body's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, ſure I am, the Perſons concern'd in this Solemnity muſt in all good ſenſe be granted to believe it. Theſe expenſive Funerals beſpeak our Faith, that <hi>this dead Body</hi> ſhall ariſe. For it was ſmartly urged by <hi>Tertullian</hi> againſt ſome Heathens that believ'd it not, that their coſt was vain which with a Ridiculous profuſeneſs they laid out up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Dead, becauſe they had no hopes they ſhould again Live. Alas! If we thought theſe poor Remains were never to be us'd more, it
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:99507:17"/>
were more Reaſonable we left them with more neglect. But ſince we know they ſhall be call'd for by the Trump of God, and hope they will become Veſſels of Immortal Honour, 'tis now Piety and Duty in us to lay them decently and ſafely up, and our Faith concerning their Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection is a ſolid Argument to juſtifie our doing ſo. And if any <hi>Judas,</hi> upon obſerving the Pomp of this Solemnity, ſhould ask to what purpoſe is this waſte? Our Saviour's anſwer will be our beſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, That what is done is done for the Burial, and as a Pious Teſtimony of our Faith, that the Dead Body ſhall ariſe.</p>
            <p>Upon the ſuppoſition of which, I proceed,</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> To ſhew for what ſingular Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons the laſt end of the Righteous is incomparably moſt deſireable; ſo that it will be our Wiſdom, not only to wiſh it may be our own, but in the mean time ſeriouſly to endeavour it may be ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Precious,</hi> ſays the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Pſ.</hi> 116.15. <hi>in the ſight of the Lord is the Death of his Saints;</hi> and in all Senſes of the Words (they having more Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions than one) 'tis true that good Men are very dear to God; and with a peculiar diſtinction from the wicked and prophane, 'tis evident at the Death of both. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Death to the Righteous comes ſtript of all its
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:99507:17"/>
Spiritual Horrors. Tho' it may aſſault his fleſhly Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with Swoons and Agonies, every ſtep it advances, yet the Tranquility of his mind is ſtill the ſame, and the conſolations of his Spirit do often appear Superior in the conflict, tho' the anguiſh of the Body be never ſo extream.</p>
            <p>But turn now your eyes upon a poor Creature that has been brought up delicately, and by the uninterrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed enjoyment of ſenſual pleaſures, has rockt his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence 'till this moment dead aſleep; when the Harbingers of Death of a ſudden draw back the curtains, and ſhe awakes, with what diſtraction does it view it ſelf! But then to look upwards, and behold his God, whom he wiſh'd an Idol, appearing in all the terrible Array of an Omnipotent Avenger, when the amaz'd wretch that would never believe it was a God that dyed to ſave him, begins to apprehend himſelf was the Murderer that ſpilt his Blood; we need not wonder at the fright He is in upon ſuch a proſpect; and ſure he can tell you, there is a vaſt difference, in the laſt end, between the Righteous and the Wicked. For,</p>
            <p n="2">2. When the Righteous dye there is a full end of all their Troubles: Death is their laſt Enemy, and he diſarmed, that he can ſting no more. But to wicked and Impenitent Sinners, except the Truth of God can fail for ever, this Death will begin their endleſs miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. The preſent Life is to the moſt faithful Servants of Chriſt, for the moſt part, a ſtate of hardſhip, for 'tis a perpetual warfare. They have innumerable Enemies, and theſe for the moſt part in ambuſcade: The ſnares that are laid for them, often give them falls, and then the Bruiſe is long a Curing, and the Operation of the Medicine painful and afflictive. And St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> makes ſuch a moving deſcription of this matter, that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:99507:18"/>
he wonders how any pious Soul can forbear longing for Death, or refrain running into Martyrdom. And St. <hi>Jerome,</hi> in an Epiſtle to the <hi>Roman Lady Paulina,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting her for the Death of her Daughter, tells her, this World is only a troubled Sea; yea tho' it were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo calm, yet the breadth and length of the Waters on which we float here is frightful, ſo that, <hi>Solus exitus eſt ſecuritatis portus,</hi> we muſt quit the Stage, if ever we would be free from the Apprehenſions of the Tragedy.</p>
            <p>Accordingly Death does certainly put a Period to all theſe Troubles, and more, it tranſlates all good Men to ſuch a ſtate of pure unmingled Joys, where there are no ſorrows to embitter, no melancholy to Eclipſe, nor any Temptation can come, to moleſt them in, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them of their Joys. And,</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> There is no compariſon between the end of theſe two ſorts of Men, in another Reſpect ſtill, <hi>viz.</hi> of that honourable memory that is preſerved after Death of the <hi>one,</hi> whilſt Stench, not Perfume, gives the <hi>other</hi> a Remembrance; who would immediately be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, were it not for what is regiſtred to their Infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and diſgrace.</p>
            <p>Whereas a good Man's Character, like a true Medal, acquires value and veneration by its Age. His name has the Influence of a Law, upon thoſe that come after him, and his Example is a Rule, which all Wiſe Men will obey and imitate. Yea thoſe that will not do ſo, will yet pay a deference to it, and wiſh they could; and I believe there are few in the world, as corrupt as 'tis, but will own, when they are in earneſt, that they had rather be <hi>Job</hi> upon the Dunghil than <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great.</p>
            <p>So that if we conſider the confidence, wherewith Holy Men are encouraged to expect Death, or the Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99507:18"/>
wherewith they undergo it, or the Happineſs they are let into by paſſing through it, or the Honour and Veneration wherewith their names are embalm'd after it, we ſee ſufficient reaſon to juſtifie <hi>Balaam</hi>'s wiſh, and to prompt us to the utmoſt endeavour, in preparing to <hi>dye the death of the Righteous, and that our laſt end be like his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now what if I ſhould ſay, that what was this wicked Man's fruitleſs wiſh, was this excellent Lady's Wiſdom providently to ſecure.</p>
            <p>I know, and therefore dare appeal to all that knew her, that She was very early ſo wiſe as ſeriouſly to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her latter end; following his Example, who was her great Maſter, to Inſtruct her in the Art of Devotion; and as he did, ſo did She carry her Soul continually in her hand, as well to obſerve its Dangers, as to be in conſtant readineſs to reſign it; for I ſcarce ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member to have converſt with her, but firſt or laſt She made that Subject part of the entertainment. And ſure; what was ſo frequently her grave diſcourſe, could not be ſeldom her Solemn Meditation. And I have been told, by ſuch as had the moſt opportunities to obſerve her, That, as early as She could underſtand or learn any thing, She ſhew'd an Inclination to covet the knowledge of the beſt things.</p>
            <p>The care of her Parents in her Virtuous Education, She ſo ingeniouſly requited, by ſuch an uniform and Dutiful obſervance of them from her Childhood to her Marriage, that I heard her once very ſeriouſly juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by one of them, in theſe expreſs words; That thro' her whole Life-time She had ſcarce done any thing to offend them. And from ſo ſteady a Piety ſhewn to her Earthly Parents, She made her Aſſent eaſie to that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99507:19"/>
elevated Devotion, wherewith She diſcharged her Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to her Father which is in Heaven.</p>
            <p>Thoſe Books, which ſome People make all their Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, She would never be tempted to make her Recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Her taſte was adapted only to ſolid Truth, She had no reliſh of Romantic Vanity.</p>
            <p>She had the Felicity of a ſevere Temper, that could not be pleaſed with any diſcourſe that in the leaſt threatned to taint her imagination, or ſtain the purity of her mind. Inſtructive Hiſtories She choſe for her Divertion; but her ſtudious Application nothing could command, but ſuch Books as darted in Light upon her mind to diſcover her Duty, and Heat to enflame her with Zeal to practiſe it. And for this purpoſe She very early began to uſe the beſt Arts of converſing with God, and her own Soul: In the Splendours of a Court (for ſuch was her Fathers Houſe) She one day in the week conſtantly ſpent in the Retirements of her Cloſet; and in Conformity to the Diſcipline of the Church, her ſtated day was either <hi>Wedneſday</hi> or <hi>Friday,</hi> which of them She foreſaw She might be beſt permitted to make her own, and obſerve Chriſt's direction, in faſting at a time when ſhe ſhould leaſt appear unto men to faſt.</p>
            <p>This account was given me by a Reverend Perſon, that had the Honour and pleaſure to Miniſter to the Family in the Offices of Religion; and with this ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing Remark upon this noble Saint, that he always obſerved her on thoſe days, after ſhe had finiſh'd the holy Labours of them, ſhe was ever more chearful in Humour, brighter and more agreeable in her converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Air, than She was uſed to be at any other time. Which ſhew'd, that as ſhe took great care not to play the Hypocrite with the World, ſo She took true
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:99507:19"/>
pains, not to deal deceitfully with her Soul. For 'tis very obſervable, that theſe corporal ſeverities often operate to quite contrary effects; and where they are overtly or inſincerely managed, they only exaſperate and enrage our Luſts, not kill them, and a whole days humiliation only ſerves to make the miſtaken Votary more fretful, and peeviſh, prouder, and more cenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, <hi>i. e.</hi> worſe diſpoſed for Converſation, either with God or Man, than he was before.</p>
            <p>But to dedicate a day to Faſting and Prayer, and holy Meditation, and afterward come forth with a ſerene Aſpect, a chearful Countenance, and an humble, condeſcenſive, and obliging behaviour, this ſhews that one has got the Maſtery over thoſe Appetites, whoſe Chaſtiſement he undertook, and the Beaſt is tam'd and made obedient by our diſcipline.</p>
            <p>Thus did this young <hi>Aſcetic</hi> ſo very early attain to what St <hi>Paul</hi> called <hi>a Keeping under the Body,</hi> which could not have been done at that Age, but by ſuch a meaſure of Divine Grace, as in all likelihood would have been and was ſufficient for her in her ſtrongeſt Temptations.</p>
            <p>Beſides this, She was accuſtom'd at thoſe years to that which prov'd of Infinite uſe to her, to the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of her progreſs in the buſineſs of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. And that was to riſe early, daily: When the firſt thing She did, was devoutly to acknowledge the mercy of God, who had watch'd over her whilſt She had ſlept: Thus ſeaſoning her mind be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the Morning, She ſeemed to have a grateful ſavour of it all the Day after; and when it could be, without Obſervation, She diverted to her Cloſet at Noon, that no diſtinct Period of her time might
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:99507:20"/>
eſcape her Conſecration of her ſelf and it to Gods Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Glory.</p>
            <p>She was moreover extreamly laborious in her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations for the Lords Supper, which She would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver neglect, unleſs when She thought She had not due and timely Notice of the Day of its Miniſtration. The Hunger and Thirſt She had after this heavenly Food, was always more Eager than her Appetite to her Meals. She felt this quick and Importunate in her, even in her laſt Convulſions, when to every thing elſe her deſire fail'd. And in the extremity of that Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs She was in, ſo near her Diſſolution, her Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion recover'd its wonted Vigour, and her Spirit ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd able to actuate her Body, under the very Arreſts of Death, to bear its ſhare of Reverence and Worſhip in that Occaſion.</p>
            <p>She had an exemplary Charity, and not leſs ſo for its Diſcretion than its Liberality. She hated a Fragment ſhould be loſt, as She once thought nothing could be which the Poor had; tho' at length She was perſwaded there was a giving which was not Charity, after which She govern'd her Charity, as She did her whole Behaviour, with great Prudence. In a word, I have too good warrant to be afraid to ſay almoſt any thing of this great Subject, that might Reflect an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour upon her Memory, who was ſo Rare an Example of almoſt every Thing praiſe worthy.</p>
            <p>To forward her growth in theſe Attainments, She was not a little obliged to the Gifts of Nature, tho' much more to the Divine Grace; as we are allowed to diſtinguiſh, tho' 'tis all of Grace. She had a high Birth, which by being dignified by a holy Calling, gave Her vaſt Advantages of Commanding and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving her own Time, and ſet Her above the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:99507:20"/>
or the Temptation of waſting it upon imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Viſits. Her bodily Structure was Beautiful and Exact, which being ſuitably informed and animated by a Devout Soul, added to her the further Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a moſt chaſt Converſation. And by all theſe together ſhe deſervedly challeng'd the heighth of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>'s Character, for as her Lord was her Head, ſo She was his Crown.</p>
            <p>Her Averſions were ſtrong to whatever was ſhameful or diſhonourable, either in principles or practice. And I have obſerv'd her, to expreſs a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar diſlike to that mean, but prevailing Cuſtom, of ſerving up to the preſent Company, the faults or fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of the abſent. In ſhort, She eſteemed that the beſt Breeding, which came neareſt the Rule and Example of her Saviour; and when all is done, Religion forms us to the beſt manners in the World.</p>
            <p>And this was it which made this Lady ſome times take ſuch State upon Her, as to give occaſion for a miſtake in judging of the courteſie and humility of her Temper, which Religion had made natural to her. For She would never put up an Affront offer'd to God or Religion, without ſhewing her Reſentments, which could not but gain her ſuch an inward Eſteem, among all People of Worth or Honour, as more than compenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for what She loſt of outward Complement and Reſpect, from ſome other Perſons. And now to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe her Deportment under her bodily Afflictions, of which She had a great ſhare, is a task too hard for any one that wants thoſe Tryals, and that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Patience, and pious Reſignation wherewith She bore them. This is certain; By theſe fatherly Diſciplines She was trained up, and admirably ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh'd for the diſcharge of her Duty in all thoſe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:99507:21"/>
Stations and Relations the Divine Providence had appointed her to ſuſtain. And I truly believe She did ſo.</p>
            <p>That her Parents have abſolv'd her, I have already ſaid; That her Lord has too, ſince her conjugal State, I am able to teſtifie in ſuch a manner, that 'tis not fit to be Reported, 'till He is himſelf removed above the Eccho of it. And I am ſure no Man can do juſtice to his noble Character, with reſpect to his Behaviour towards his Dear Lady, but he muſt diſtaſte his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, and make his Complement an Offence.</p>
            <p>To her Servants and Dependants She was a Nurſing Mother; to her Acquaintance an obliging Friend; and to all her Relatives and Allies, She even exceeded in Tenderneſs and Affection. So that She having with ſuch almoſt unexampl'd Arts of Piety and Solicitude acquitted her ſelf to her Parents, with all filial Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; to her dear and ſure now moſt diſconſolate Lord with all Ingenuous conjugal Affection; and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to all the World with untainted Honour; and to her God and Saviour with a pure Conſcience, She is gone, where her warfare is at an end, and where her Triumphs are begun, that are never to have an end. <hi>To which God of his Infinite mercy,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
